Today's דף Daf is גיטין Gittin ס"ב, Samech-Bet, sixty-two. We pick up
on the last few lines of ס"א עמוד ב'. Samech-Aleph amud Bet.
We are wrapping up the fifth פרק perek of הניזקין, HaNizakin, which
has moved from the fourth פרק'ס perek's discussion of things that are
done for תיקון עולם Tikkun Olam to now discussion of things that
were done for דרכי שלום, Darchei Shalom, ways of peace. And the
משנה Mishnah mentioned ways in which a woman would lend, was allowed
to lend, various implements for making, grinding and making flour and kneading
dough to her friend who might not have been keeping the laws
of שמיטה Shmittah or might have been an עם הארץ Am Ha'aretz
and not keeping תרומות Trumot and מעשרות Ma'asrot and so on, and
that nevertheless certain things were allowed because of דרכי שלום. Darchei Shalom.
So in the context of that, the גמרא Gemara got into a
whole discussion about whether we're concerned that when one
entrusts foodstuffs with an עם הארץ Am Ha'aretz or with various people,
will they swap it out for their own and do we have
to be concerned or will they touch it, do we have to
be concerned that it will become טמא tamei or that we will
get back produce that has not had תרומות מעשרות Trumot Ma'asrot taken
from it? So we're wrapping that up. We have one last case
about that and we're at the bottom of ס"א עמוד ב'. Samech-Aleph
amud Bet. And the גמרא Gemara says the following: והא קתני לאלמא
לא חיישינן. V'hakati l'alma lo chaishinan. This is one, two, five lines
from the bottom. I still want to ask, says the גמרא, Gemara,
is it true that we're not concerned that under normal circumstances—there might
be special circumstances that we dealt with yesterday that we're concerned about
swapping, but the claim is in general we're not concerned, you can
entrust this stuff to an עם הארץ Am Ha'aretz or whatever and
we're not concerned that it'll be swapped out with other foods. Is
that really true, says the גמרא? Gemara? והתניא, V'hatanya, we taught a
ברייתא, Braita, תוספתא טהרות: Tosefta Taharot: אשת חבר טוחנת עם אשת עם
הארץ בזמן שהיא טמאה אבל לא בזמן שהיא טהורה. Eshet chaver tochenet
im eshet am ha'aretz bizman she'hi t'meiah aval lo bizman she'hi t'horah.
So the wife of a חבר, chaver, and here חבר chaver in
the sense of somebody who is מקפיד makpid on the laws of
טומאה וטהרה, tumah v'taharah, can grind the grain with the wife of
an עם הארץ Am Ha'aretz and again the assumption of course being
that the wives are following the same practices as the husbands. When
this woman is טמאה, t'meiah, presumably means when she's a נידה niddah
or טמאה t'meiah for any other reason. אבל, Aval, but not when
she is טהורה. t'horah. What's the difference? Because she will follow the
practices that she's used to at home, this wife of the חבר,
chaver, and at home when she's טמאה t'meiah she can still grind
the grain as long as she doesn't touch it and she won't
make it טמא. tamei. So she'll be in the habit here of
not touching the grain. But if she's טהורה, t'horah, then she might
come to handle the food and pop some food in her mouth
and that will be food that will not have had תרומות ומעשרות
Trumot u'Ma'asrot taken from it. So therefore we don't want her to
do it, it'll be too likely that she might come to inadvertently
eat from it if she's טהורה. t'horah. רבי שמעון בן אלעזר אומר
אף בזמן שהיא טמאה לא תטחן. Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar omer af
bizman she'hi t'meiah lo titchan. No, no, no, even when she's טמאה
t'meiah she shouldn't grind, even though she won't absent-mindedly put some food
in her mouth, מפני שחברתה נותנת לה אוכל, mipnei she'chavertah notenet lah
ochel,
but because we are afraid that the friend that she's helping out,
the wife of the עם הארץ, Am Ha'aretz, top of ס"ב עמוד
א' Samech-Bet amud Aleph now,
will go ahead and offer her some of the food. Hey, you
know, we've been working at grinding and at making this stuff, etc.,
maybe here, maybe you want to eat some. And then it won't
be absent-minded
and she might come ahead and come to eat it, maybe the
social pressure or whatever, even though she is
טמאה. t'meiah. So therefore the גמרא Gemara says that that is actually
according to רבי שמעון בן אלעזר, Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar, that's a
concern. Now why is that relevant at all to the issue of
entrusting food?
השתא מגנב גנבה חילופי לא מחלפה? Hashta mignav ganva chilufei lo mechalfa?
So here, this woman, this wife of the עם הארץ, Am Ha'aretz,
is prepared to steal. So of course she'll swap out food that's
entrusted to her. Now where is she stealing? So if you look
at רש"י, Rashi, רש"י Rashi says: נותנת לה אלמא חשידה אשת עם
הארץ לגנוב משל בעלה ולתת לחברתה. Notenet lah alma chasheida eshet am
ha'aretz lignov mishel ba'alah u'latet l'chavertah. To steal from her husband and
to give to her friend.
Presumably her husband owns all the food in the house, the husband
was the bread earner, winner, and therefore she did not have a
right to offer food to her friends without her husband's permission. So
effectively she's stealing from her husband. So if she's going to steal
from her husband, so you see you can't trust עמי הארץ amei
ha'aretz and therefore if they're going to steal they'll certainly swap out
stuff if they like the stuff you entrusted better than theirs, they'll
swap it out. And therefore how can you make this claim that
we can entrust things with them? אמר רב יוסף התם נמי מורה
ואמרה. Amar Rav Yosef hatam nami moreh v'amrah. No, no, no, that's
also a special case. She, this woman is
מורה היתר, moreh hetter, she rationalizes why that's allowed. תורא מדשי כאכיל.
Tora m'dashi k'achil. Because an ox should be able to eat from
what it's threshing, you know, there's a הלכה halacha in the תורה
Torah that if your ox is threshing you can't muzzle it. My
friend is here, she's helping me grind the grain, so even though
I don't have explicit permission from my husband
to share this food with her, it's totally fine, I'm sure he'd
be okay with it. And therefore, that's why she's doing it, but
it does not... tell you that somebody will
self-consciously swap out the food when they cannot rationalize it in this
type of a way.
They actually I think they did a study once where they put
like a dollar out
in a what do you call like in a common area in
work, like in like the kitchen area and nobody touched it. But
then they put out a soda can and people came and they
took it and they drank it because taking a dollar that's not
yours that feels like stealing. Taking a soda can that's been abandoned
that doesn't feel like stealing. So people have interesting ways of rationalizing
these different scenarios, but as a general thing we are not concerned
that they are going to swap out the food. Okay, so that's
really an end of the conversation yesterday. Now we are a little
bit switch gears. העיד רב יוסי Heid Rav Yossi so three lines
from the top of ס"ב עמוד א. Samech Beis Amud Aleph. העיד
רב יוסי בן משולם משום רב יוחנן Heid Rav Yossi ben Meshullam
mishum Rav Yochanan רב יוסי בן משולם Rav Yossi ben Meshullam testified
in the name of רב יוחנן Rav Yochanan אחיו achiv his brother
שמשום רבי אלעזר בן חסמא she-mishum Rabbi Elazar ben Chasma that said
in the name of רבי אלעזר בן חסמא Rabbi Elazar ben Chasma
אין עושין חלת עם הארץ בטהרה. Ein osin challas am ha'aretz b'taharah.
You cannot if you are טהור tahor this is a following up
before we talked about the wife of the חבר chaver being טמא
tamei or טהור tahor where ironically it was more permissible when she
was טמאה tamei etc. Here you are
talking now to a person who is a kneader
K-N-E-A-D-E-R who goes ahead and kneads dough and an עם הארץ am
ha'aretz comes and gives you the dough and says I want you
to knead this into me bake חלות challas for me it's a
lot of very laborious in order to do all that kneading and
by the way while you're doing it please do me a favor
and do הפרשת חלה. hafrashas challah. Take out a little bit of
the bread of the dough to give to a כהן. kohen. And
that's great because here you are you're a חבר chaver you're טהור
tahor
and you'll separate it out and that'll give it to the עם
הארץ am ha'aretz and he'll give it to the כהן. kohen. But
it says no actually when you're טהור tahor it's a problem. Why?
Because you might be טהור tahor but the dough that was given
to you because it comes from an עם הארץ am ha'aretz we're
assuming is טמא. tamei. And therefore since it's טמא tamei dough you'll
take it out the כהן kohen will see the עם הארץ am
ha'aretz the עם הארץ am ha'aretz will come back he'll get back
his bread and the חלה challah the thing that goes to the
כהן kohen he'll give it to the כהן kohen he'll say yeah
so and so separated it out for me and the כהן kohen
knows you're a חבר chaver and you're טהור tahor and therefore the
כהן kohen will think that the dough is טהור tahor but actually
it's not because it came from an עם הארץ am ha'aretz who's
טמא. tamei. So therefore that's a problem.
But if you're טהור tahor but so אין עושין חלת עם הארץ
בטהרה אבל עושין עיסת חוליו בטהרה Ein osin challas am ha'aretz b'taharah
aval osin issas chulyav b'taharah ונוטל הימנו כדי חלה ומניחה בכפישה
או באנחוסא. binotel heimenu k'dei challah uminichah b'kefishah o b'anchusah.
So what you can do however is you can make it into
dough. If he delivers you flour then you flour by it's not
yet טמא tamei it's only once water hits it and becomes dough
that it could become טמא. tamei. So if he delivers you the
flour you can turn it into dough and then separate it out
בטהרה b'taharah and then it really is טהור חלה. tahor challah. Okay
and then now it's going to be on the עם הארץ am
ha'aretz to deliver to a כהן. kohen. So you want to make
sure that it's going to remain טהור. tahor. So what do you
do? You put it in this thing a כפישה kefishah or an
אנחוסא anchusah which is רש"י Rashi explains so רש"י Rashi explains these
are some like unusual vessels. רש"י Rashi explains that this is like
a worn out type of a flask or the גאונים Geonim explain
that the אנחוסא anchusah is a like a flat wooden board. So
you go ahead and you put it in these unusual vessels וכשבא
עם הארץ ליטול נוטל את שתיהן ואין חושש. u-kshe-ba am ha'aretz litol
notel es shteihen v'ein choshesh.
And he takes both meaning both the dough or the חלה challah
that you baked with it
and the halachic חלה challah that goes to the כהן kohen and
you're not concerned that he's going to touch it. You keep it
in the vessel he's going to keep it in the vessel and
we assume that he's going to deliver it in the vessel to
the כהן kohen he's not going to touch it. Why we're allowed
to concern that is an interesting question which we'll see in a
minute. ואין עושין תרומת זיתיו בטהרה. Ve-ein osin trumas zeisav b'taharah.
Similarly
you do not go ahead and press his olives when you're טהור
tahor and then he asks you while you're done pressing my olives
you're the guy that owned the olive press you're a חבר chaver
go ahead and be מפריש תרומה mafrish truma for me and give
it to the כהן. kohen. Same concern. He's giving you the olives.
There were two stages in olive production. There's the crushing of the
olives and then the pressing of the olives. So the crushing is
they like this big stone wheel that they went around it and
around with the olives in a basket and that basically crushed them
and start the juices start to come out. And then the next
stage was an olive press where it was an enormous over long
period of time degree of pressure put down that really squoze out
all of the juice. Okay so if you're giving to him after
they've been crushed and ask him to press it that's a problem
because once they've been crushed and the liquid comes out the liquid
comes in contact to the olive similar to the water with the
flour and it makes them possible for it to become טמא. tamei.
So the עם הארץ am ha'aretz delivers it to you, so you're
getting טמא tamei olives, so if you're going to now separate it
out and you're טהור, tahor, the כהן kohen is going to think
the תרומה terumah is טהור tahor and that's going to be a
problem. So that you are not allowed to do. אבל עושין זיתים
חוליו בטהרה, aval osin zeisim chulyav b'tahara,
but you can go ahead and make his זיתים zeisim when they
are חולין, chullin, you can do it בטהרה, b'tahara, it's not exactly
clear how that means something different, but the point here is you
can actually take the olives before they've been crushed, crushed and and
do the crushing, and then they will because you got them before
they were crushed, they were טהור, tahor, that you can do, and
therefore the תרומה terumah will be טהור, tahor, ונוטל ממנו כדי תרומה
ומניחה בכלי חבר, v'notel mimenu k'dei terumah u'minicha bikli chever,
and there you put it in one of your own vessels
and that is טהור. tahor. וכשבא עם הארץ ליטול נוטל את שניהם
ואינו חושש. u'ch'sheba am ha'aretz litol notel es sheihem v'eino choshesh. And
the עם הארץ am ha'aretz takes them, the crushed olives and the
olive oil you produced for him plus the stuff that is to
be given to the כהן, kohen, and you don't have to be
afraid that he's going to touch it. Now, it did not mention
some of those unusual vessels before, and one of the explanations is
that those unusual vessels were basically sort of like flat boards and
therefore that is not going to be a good place that you're
going to be able to store crushed olives.
Okay, now, וטעמא מאי. v'ta'ama mai. So now the גמרא Gemara says,
why are we allowing this? I mean, we get why we're restricting
it, but why do we allow the cases we do allow? We
should be concerned that the עם הארץ am ha'aretz will touch it.
So אמר רבי יוחנן משום כדי חיי דגבל ומשום כדי חיי דבדד,
amar rabbi yochanan mishum k'dei chayei d'gaval u'mishum k'dei chayei d'badad, because
of the,
because we want to help the פרנסה, parnasa, you know, we want
to help them make a living for this bread dough kneader and
the olive crusher.
And the most of the people were not חברים, chaveirim, they were
עמי הארץ, amei ha'aretz, and it probably would be help your business
if you were allowed to be the one to separate off תרומה,
terumah, and therefore we did this to accommodate in order to make
it easier for them to make a living. Okay, וצריכא. u'tzricha. Now,
and you know, and similar to it's a type of an allowance
besides that we're talking about עמי הארץ amei ha'aretz and חבר, chaver,
and that's analogous to the previous discussion, it's also similar to the
allowance in our משנה mishna where you're allowed to lend your friend
something, that was not כדי חיי, k'dei chayei, that was not about
economics and making a living, that was about דרכי שלום, darchei shalom,
but obviously there's a similar type allowance in terms of the interactions
of חברים chaveirim and עמי הארץ. amei ha'aretz. Okay, וצריכא, v'tzricha, and
you need to tell me both cases, both of the kneader and
of the olive press, excuse me. דאי אשמעינן גבל, d'ei ashmi'inan gaval,
if you'd just told me about the dough kneader, משום דלא נפיש
אגריה, mishum d'lo nafish agrei, it's a very small margin of profit
that that person
makes, so you understand that you want to give a permit in
that case. אבל בדד דנפיש אגריה, aval badad d'nafish agrei, but the
guy who owns the olive press, you know, he has a nice,
he makes a lot of profit. So אימא לא, eima lo, so
maybe we would not be so accommodating. דאי אשמעינן בדד, d'ei ashmi'inan
badad, if you told me the case of the guy with the
olive press, משום דלא שכיח ליה, mishum d'lo shechi'ach lei, that's because
there's only a certain season, excuse me, I keep on saying I
said wine press again, olive press. If we say the case of
the guy with the olive press, that's because there's only a certain
season in which, it's true he makes a nice profit, but only
there's a very limited season in which he is doing this. So
it's
true that he makes a nice profit, but he's got to support
himself the whole year by the money that he makes during the
olive pressing season. So therefore maybe we'll make an especial accommodation.
So משום דלא שכיח ליה. mishum d'lo shechi'ach lei. אבל גבל דשכיח
ליה, aval gaval d'shechi'ach lei, but the guy who's doing the bread
kneading, the dough kneading, you know, that's a year-round business. אימא לא,
eima lo, maybe we don't have to accommodate. צריכא, tzricha, so it's
telling you we yes for both reasons we accommodate in order to
help them make a living. Now we're going to ask the question:
it's very nice that you want to accommodate, but how are you
really attending to the halakhic issues? אמר מר, amar mar, נוטל ממנו
כדי חלה ומניחה בכפיש ובאנתסא וכשבא עם הארץ ליטול נוטל את שניהם
ואינו חושש. notel mimenu k'dei challah u'minicha bikfish u'v'antasa u'ch'sheba am ha'aretz
litol notel es sheihem v'eino choshesh. You take the חלה challah from
this bread now that you're doing it בטהרה b'tahara and the dough
is
טהור, tahor, and you put it in these special vessels, and the
עם הארץ am ha'aretz takes them and you don't have to be
concerned. Now, again, the concern could be just that he'll make the
חלה challah טמא, tamei, but even a bigger concern is he'll make
the חלה challah טמא tamei and give it to a כהן kohen
and the כהן kohen will think that it's טהור tahor and eat
טמא tamei חלה, challah, which is a real serious sin. So the
גמרא Gemara says, ווליחוש דילמא נגע בה, v'leichosh dilma naga bah, why
not be concerned that he's going to touch it? So it says
דאמרינן ליה, d'amrinan lei, because we say to him the following: חזי
אי נגעת בה הדר לטיבלא. chazi ei nagat bah hadar l'tivla. We
basically lie to him and we say, you know, he's an עם
הארץ, am ha'aretz, so not only is he not that מקפיד makpid
on laws of טומאה וטהרה, tumah v'tahara, he's also not that or
הפרשת חלה, hafrashas challah, there's a reason he asked you to be
מפריש חלה. mafrish challah. So he's not only is he not too
מקפיד, makpid, he's also somewhat ignorant of it. So therefore we tell
him, okay, I took the חלה challah you asked me to take,
I put it in this special vessel, but you have to understand
that if you touch it, it's going to make everything revert back
to be טבל, tevel, and then it's going to be forbidden to
eat. And he doesn't want to eat טבל, tevel, right? The general
assumption is even though we have all this principle of דמאי. demai.
That רוב עמי הארץ מעשרין הן, rov amei ha'aretz me'asrin hen, that
they do take תרומות ומעשרות, terumos u'ma'asros, they do care about טבל,
tevel, okay? And certainly about תרומה, terumah, certainly about חלה. challah. So
therefore we lie to him and we scare him and that will
keep him from touching this. So now the גמרא Gemara says,
וליחוש דלמא לא אכפת ליה? v'leichoosh dilma lo ichpas lei? Okay, but
maybe he doesn't care, you know, I just said he did care,
but how do you know, maybe he doesn't care that it's going
to turn back into טבל? tevel? So it says no, השתא לתקוני
קמכוין מיכפת לא איכפת ליה? hashta l'sikuni k'michavein michpas lo ichpas lei?
What do you mean? He's asking the guy who's kneading the dough,
he says please take חלה challah for me. So clearly even if
there are some עמי הארץ amei ha'aretz who don't care, this one
clearly does care. So he wants it done properly. So therefore you
just say this, he might not care about טומאה וטהרה, tumah v'taharah,
okay, but he cares about the bread having חלה challah taken from
it. So therefore you use that and that's a way that you
scare him that he won't go ahead and touch this dough. Okay,
אמר מר, amar mar, נוטל הימנה כדי חלה ומניחה בסל, notel mimenu
k'dei challah u'menicha b'sal, that's the first part about the חלה. challah.
Now we're going to get to the second part. About the תרומה.
terumah. כדי תרומה ומניחה בכליו של חבר, k'dei terumah u'menicha b'kailiv shel
chaver, you take the תרומה, terumah, וכשבא עם הארץ ליטול נוטל את
שתיהן ואינו חושש. u'kesheba am ha'aretz litol notel es shteihen v'eino choshesh.
And again, same story, you give him then, you give him the
pressed olives and you give him the stuff that was תרומה terumah
and he's going to deliver the תרומה terumah to a כהן. kohen.
וליחוש דלמא נגע בה, v'leichoosh dilma naga bah, okay, let's be concerned
that he'll touch it.
Now, now you can give the same answer, you tell him if
you touch it it will turn back to being טבל. tevel. Ah,
but there's a difference, because here we did not talk about putting
it into a special vessel. So that's what the גמרא Gemara focuses
on. בשלמא התם אית ליה היכירא, bishlama hasam is lei hikeira, there
it's a very unusual vessel you put it in, okay, and therefore,
you know, when he wants to go touch it, he'll see it
and he'll remember, you know, you held out the vessel for him,
you know, and you said if you open this, if you touch
it, everything is going to be ruined. And it's so he's going
to remember because he'll see it and it'll be a, like it'll
be a visual, you know, jar, you know, a thing that makes
him, that makes him remember the warning and to stay off.
So בשלמא התם אית ליה
היכירא הכא מאי היכירא אית ליה?
bishlama hasam is
lei hikeira hacha mai hikeira is lei? Here you just gave it
to him in a normal vessel. It says you've given it to
him in your vessel. So your vessel is טהור tahor but it's
a normal vessel. So nothing is going to be unusual about that,
there's not going to be any type of a, you know, of
something like, like a visual marker and he'll just open up a
bag and start munching from it. So how are you going to
prevent that from happening? The warning won't be enough unless he remembers
the warning. So the גמרא Gemara says דמנח ליה בכלי גללים בכלי
אבנים בכלי אדמה. d'manach lei b'chlei glalim b'chlei avanim b'chlei adamah. You
put it in types of a vessel that are not only are
they טהור, tahor, they are, they are, they are not able to
become טמא. tamei. This is a vessel that is made either from
like dried dung or out of stone or out of dirt but
it's not pottery. And those types of vessels cannot even become טמא,
tamei, okay? So but they also, so that has a benefit number
one that if he touches it he won't make it טמא. tamei.
The other case of a vessel was like a flat board we
said that's out of wood, so that also would not be טמא.
tamei. So it would only be a problem if he touched the
food, not if he touched the vessel. And this has the benefit
of also being a very unusual type of a vessel, okay? And
therefore similar to the previous example it is something that, that visually
he'll see it and he'll remember, he won't just absent-mindedly eat from
it and he'll remember the warning you gave him. So the גמרא
Gemara says אי הכי מאי איריא יד דחבר אפילו דעם הארץ נמי?
ee hachi mai irya yad d'chaver afilu d'am ha'aretz nami? Why does
it have to be the vessels of a חבר? chaver? Could be
even the vessels of an עם הארץ, am ha'aretz, because these things
never become טמא, tamei, it doesn't matter what you do to them.
הכי נמי קאמר, hachi nami ka'amar, the גמרא Gemara says yeah, yeah,
yeah, that's what it means. בכלים של עם הארץ שראויים להשתמש בהן
חבר. b'chailim shel am ha'aretz she're'uyim l'hishtamesh bahen chaver. When it says
the חבר's chaver כלים, keilim, why does it have to, it means
כלים keilim that even the חבר chaver could use, כלים, keilim, vessels
that are, cannot become טמא tamei so even the vessel an עם
הארץ am ha'aretz could use it and you put it in those
vessels. Little bit of a stretch but anyway that is an end
of the discussion of the עם הארץ am ha'aretz and the חבר
chaver and their interactions which is both a concern of, you know,
a range of different concerns. The משנה's Mishnah concern was are you
assisting them in doing an עבירה? aveirah? The גמרא's Gemara concern is
starts to talk about the concern of are we concerned that they're
going to swap food that you entrusted to them so then you'll
take it back and you'll eat טבל tevel because it'll have been
swapped? And now we're dealing with an issue about you trying to
help them take תרומות terumos and חלה challah which is a very
praiseworthy thing, but we have to be concerned that the חלה challah
remains טהור tahor and that it gets to the כהן kohen in
that state. And that was an allowance not because of social interaction
and דרכי שלום darchei shalom but an allowance of כדי חייה k'dei
chayei for people to make a פרנסה parnassah as long as certain
safeguards were put in place, even though they included lying, which the
גמרא Gemara seems to be not so concerned about. Okay, so now
we get to the next part of the משנה, Mishnah, the final
part of the משנה, Mishnah, which says that you are allowed to
מחזיקין ידי עובדי כוכבים בשביעית, machzikin yedei ovdei kochavim b'shvi'is, עובדי כוכבים
akum בשביעית. bishvi'is. You're able to say to, to non-Jews who are
working the land during שמיטה Shmita like you're strengthening them. So what
strengthening them exactly means we'll see in the גמרא, Gemara, but, but,
you, but... You understand here that this is partly דרכי שלום, darchei
shalom, but maybe even more than דרכי שלום. darchei shalom. Since Jews
can't work the land,
the fact that non-Jews are working the land might be essential for
in order to be able to survive during the during שמיטה. Shmita.
So you actually want to encourage them and that's מחזיקין ידי אקו"ם
בשביעית. machzikin yedei akum bishviit. So let's take a look at the
גמרא Gemara because the question is how far does this מחזיקין machzikin
go? So the גמרא Gemara says as follows: מחזיקין, machzikin, you can
strengthen them? ואמר
רב דימי בר שישנא משמיה דרב, Ve'amar Rav Dimi bar Shishna mishmei
de'Rav, אין עודרין עם אקו"ם בשביעית. ein odrin im akum bishviit. So
the גמרא Gemara thinks מחזיקין machzikin similar to the first part where
it talks about lending them lending vessels to the עם הארץ am
ha'aretz or actually grinding the grain. So מחזיקין machzikin maybe means you
can work with them. So the גמרא Gemara says really?
Now doesn't רב דימי Rav Dimi say that you cannot go ahead
and that you cannot hoe with the עם הארץ am ha'aretz with
with the non-Jew on שמיטה Shmita ואין כופלין שלום לעובדי כוכבים ve'ein
kofulin shalom le'ovdei kochavim and you don't say שלום עליכם, שלום עליכם,
Shalom aleichem, shalom aleichem, you're not overly enthusiastic. The משנה Mishna says
that you do say you do the language of the משנה Mishna
was that you are שואלין בשלומן shoalin bishloman but you are not
כופלין שלום. kofulin shalom. You don't do it twice. Okay, so the
גמרא Gemara says: לא צריכא למימר להו אחזוקי בעלמא. lo tzricha le'meimar
lehu achzukei be'alma. No, what the point is that we're talking about
saying just אחזוקי, achzukei, יישר כח. yasher koach. So it's a question
how to read this גמרא. Gemara. Was the גמרא Gemara assuming that
מחזיקין machzikin meant that you could actually work with them? And could
be, and then and then we're saying that you're not allowed. Now
why would you think you could work with them? It is שמיטה.
Shmita. Well that gets to the question of whether יש קניין לאקו"ם
להפקיע מיד תרומות ומעשרות בארץ ישראל. yesh kinyan le'akum le'hafkiya miyad trumot
u'maasrot be'Eretz Yisrael. Does the non-Jewish ownership of the land allow you
to work the land on שמיטה? Shmita? I think people who know
about the היתר מכירה Heter Mechira know that that's exactly what the
idea of the היתר מכירה Heter Mechira is based on. And here
it says that you're not allowed to work with them even though
it's their land. So that's just interesting in itself, the possibility you
would be but then the גמרא Gemara rejecting it. But then really
you're not allowed? But then how does that explain what we are
actually doing in terms of the היתר מכירה? Heter Mechira? So take
a look at תוספות. Tosafot. תוספות Tosafot says here: אין עודרין עם
אקו"ם בשביעית. ein odrin im akum bishviit. תוספות Tosafot says: והא דקאמר
בפרק זה בורר v'ha de'ka'amar be'perek zeh borer גבי כהן וחורש יכול
לומר אגיסטון אני בתוכה gabbei Kohen v'choresh yachol lomar agiston ani betochah
that if you see a כהן, Kohen, for some reason mentions a
כהן, Kohen, not specifically a כהן, Kohen, who is plowing the land
on שמיטה, Shmita, he could just say oh I'm an אגיסטון agiston
and therefore not necessarily violating. So what is this אגיסטון? agiston? So
לא כמו שביאר בקונטרס ששכיר לנוכרי. lo kemo she'be'eir be'kuntres she'sechir le'nochri.
It's not like רש"י Rashi explains that he's a hired hand of
a נוכרי nochri and the נוכרי nochri owns the land. That would
not make it allowed because this גמרא Gemara says you're not allowed
to plow with them in the
land דמשמע הכא דאסור de'hashma hacha d'assur ולא מסתברא לחלק בין חינם
לבשכר ve'lo mistabra le'chalek bein chinam le'bischar and you can't say that
oh like maybe you're allowed to do it as a volunteer, that's
מחזיקין ידי אקו"ם, machzikin yedei akum, you're not allowed to do it
as a volunteer because then you're, but but if they're hiring you
maybe you're seen as more an extension of them and I don't
know somehow that would make it more allowed or maybe it's an
allowance that we give for פרנסה parnassa but technically it would be
allowed. תוספות Tosafot says I don't buy that.
אלא מפרש בנתן אגיסטון בקרקע שמקבלין מן המלך לפרוע כך וכך תבואה
בשנה. ella mefarsha be'netan agiston be'karka she'mekablin min hamalech lifroa kach ve'kach
tevuah beshanah. No no no, what it means is that they have
to pay a tax to the king. Now how does paying a
tax to the king, if it's really forbidden, allow you to work
the land on שמיטה? Shmita? So
תוספות Tosafot says מן מלך min melech et
cetera ושמא v'shema סכנת נפשות איכא אם לא יפרעו מס למלך. sakanat
nefashot ika im lo yifru mas lamelech. Maybe it would actually be
פיקוח נפשות pikuach nefashot that would allow you to violate the laws
of שמיטה. Shmita. So as opposed to explaining that גמרא Gemara that
it's allowed because the non-Jew owned the land, he says that was
a case of סכנת נפשות, sakanat nefashot, which seems a little
far-fetched. אינמי דסבר יש קניין לנוכרי בארץ להפקיע משביעית inami she'savar yesh
kinyan lenochri be'aretz le'hafkiya mishviit or no, that גמרא Gemara holds presumably
against this גמרא Gemara that a non-Jew owns it it changes its
שמיטה Shmita status. So this answer is very significant. This answer seems
to say that our גמרא Gemara and a different גמרא Gemara are
debating whether ownership of a non-Jew would change the שמיטה Shmita status
and allow it to be used on שמיטה. Shmita. And therefore based
on the other גמרא, Gemara, if you פסקן pasken that way, it
would allow the land to be plowed and used on שמיטה. Shmita.
And then תוספות Tosafot has one final one: אינמי שמיטה בזמן הזה
דרבנן. inami shmita bizman hazeh derabbanan. אף על גב דמדרבנן אסור לנוכרי
אחר גבי מלך התירו af al gav d'miderabbanan assur lenochri acher gabbei
melech hitiru or maybe because nowadays שמיטה Shmita is דרבנן, derabbanan,
we do allow it when a non-Jew owns it for special
considerations, not in general but special considerations like a tax. So those
two last answer of תוספות Tosafot are very important for the issue
of היתר מכירה. Heter Mechira. Now back to our גמרא. Gemara. So
it could be our גמרא Gemara thought that the משנה Mishna was
actually saying it was straightaway allowed, like you know maybe that other
גמרא Gemara implies, and it's to work with the non-Jewish land. And
then it says no that's not what we meant. And maybe the
גמרא Gemara also thought that כופלין kofulin meant you could go so
much to be כופל שלום. kofel shalom. maybe that was the issue.
But says no, we didn't mean either of those things, either working
the land with them or doubling up and saying a יישר כוח,
Yashkayach, השלום עליכם, Hashalom Aleichem, שלום עליכם, Shalom Aleichem, we just meant
a more simple way of encouraging them, אחזוקי. Achzuke. אחזוקי Achzuke is
like יישר כוח, Shkoyach, good job, יישר כוח, Shkoyach, but don't overdo
it. Don't be כופל שלום. kofel shalom. Okay, כי הא דרב יהודה
אמר להו אחזוקי, ki had de'Rav Yehuda amar lehu achzuka, אחזוקי. achzuka.
Like when רב יהודה Rav Yehuda saw people working the land on
שמיטה shmita he said יישר כוח. Shkoyach. רב ששת אמר להו אשרתא
Rav Sheshet amar lehu ashrasa also, like more power to you, you
know, יישר כוח. yasharkoyach. All right, so that's what you're allowed to
do for them, for the non-Jew. אין כופלין שלום לעובדי כוכבים. Ein
koflin shalom le'ovdei kochavim.
Now we're going to analyze the last part of this statement that
we brought in. This is not the משנה, mishna, second part of
this statement. רב חסדא מקדים ויהיב להו שלמא. Rav Chisda makdim ve'yahev
lehu shalma. So
you do not say שלום עליכם, Shalom Aleichem, שלום עליכם, Shalom Aleichem,
but nevertheless רב חסדא Rav Chisda made a point of going out
and saying שלום עליכם. shalom aleichem, So he said it once, he
didn't double it, but he still made a point of greeting them
and saying שלום עליכם. shalom aleichem, Or, you know, peace be on
you. Like בועז Boaz says to the קוצרים, kotzrim, השם עמכם. Hashem
imachem. רב כהנא אמר להו שלמא למר, Rav Kahana amar lehu shlama
lemar, peace to the master. Now again, is this exactly in the
שמיטה shmita context? Is this a general point about saying שלום עליכם
shalom aleichem. to non-Jews and because of דרכי שלום? darchei shalom? So
that's an interesting question of how do you read the משנה. mishna.
Right, the משנה mishna says מחזיקין ידי נכרים בשביעית אבל לא ידי
ישראל שואלין בשלומם מפני דרכי שלום. machzikin yedei nochrim bashvi'it aval lo
yedei yisrael sho'alin bishlomam mipnei darchei shalom. So whose שלום shalom are
you שואל? sho'el? Are you, you know... So רש"י Rashi says this
means the non-Jew that you can in general, nothing to do with
שמיטה shmita and working the land, when you see a non-Jew you
say hey, שלום עליכם, shalom aleichem. how are you doing? And that's
what this גמרא gemara is talking
about. People that would generally go out
and greet non-Jews שלום עליכם shalom aleichem and welcome them and so
on, and maybe just be careful not to overdo it. Okay, so
that seems to be how our גמרא gemara is reading the end
of the משנה. mishna. Another way to read the end of the
משנה mishna though, which gets us back to the first part of
the משנה mishna about helping people that are doing an עבירה, avera,
is that for Jews you're not allowed to say יישר כוח, yasharkoyach,
but you are allowed to say how are you doing, שואלין בשלומם,
sho'alin bishlomam, you know, that you are allowed to say even if
they're working the land on שמיטה. shmita. That's a little more consistent
with the beginning part of the משנה. mishna. Okay, let's go back
to the גמרא. gemara. ושואלין בשלומם. Vesho'alin bishlomam. Okay, you ask after
their well-being. Now the גמרא gemara here as said a minute ago
understands this to be talking about non-Jews. Okay, so the גמרא gemara
says השתא אחזוקי מחזיקינן שואלין בשלומם מיבעיא? hashta achzuke machzikinan sho'alin bishlomam
miba'aya? So if you can strengthen them and say יישר כוח yasharkoyach
when they're working on שמיטה, shmita, of course you can ask after
their well-being. So now it's sounding a little bit like it's going
back to talking about during שמיטה. shmita. Anyway, let's see what the
גמרא's gemara's answer is. אמר רב גביבה לא נצרכה אלא ליום חגם.
Amar Rav Geviba lo nitzrecha ela leyom chagam. Okay, okay, the end
part is not talking about שמיטה. shmita. During שמיטה shmita you can
give them encouragement, יישר כוח. yasharkoyach. But the end part of the
משנה mishna שואלין בשלומם sho'alin bishlomam is not talking about שמיטה, shmita,
it's talking about the rest of the year and not only the
rest of the year, it's even a bigger חידוש, chiddush, on their
holidays, on their festivals, where we're not supposed to do business with
them on their festivals because that's going to lead to their increased
שמחה simcha and they'll go thank their god and so on, the
whole beginning of מסכת עבודה זרה. masechet avoda zara. Nevertheless, we are
allowed to say שלום עליכם, shalom aleichem, how are you doing, and
so on, normal type of courtesy. Okay, so דתניא, detanya, we taught
in a ברייתא, braita, לא יכנס אדם לביתו של עובדי כוכבים ביום
חגו ויתן לו שלום. lo yikanes adam lebeito shel ovdei kochavim beyom
chago veyiten lo shalom. Don't overdo it. If it's their festival, don't
go into their house and ask them how they're doing, you know,
don't pay a nice social visit. That would be too much,
they'd feel too good about their connections to Jews on their holidays
and so on, and be concerned about someone encouraging them. ויתן לו
שלום מצאו בשוק, Veyiten lo shalom matzo bashuk, if you bumped into
him in the street, נותן לו בשפה רפה ובכובד ראש. noten lo
besafa rafa uvichoved rosh. You sort of say it in like, hi,
how's it going, don't be over-enthusiastic.
Okay, so on שמיטה shmita give a real encouragement. During the rest
of the year, you know, you can run up to greet them
and say שלום עליכם, shalom aleichem just certain limit, don't be כופל
שלום, kofel shalom, and on their יום חג, yom chag, you know,
you can ask but do it in a more moderate tone. Okay.
Where are we? רב הונא ורב חסדא הוו יתבי חליף ואזיל גניבא.
Rav Huna ve'Rav Chisda havay yasvei chalifei azil Gneiva. So רב הונא
Rav Huna and רב חסדא Rav Chisda were sitting and this person
by the name of גניבא, Gneiva, you might remember him from the
beginning, wonderful name, גנב Ganav or whatever, from the beginning of the
מסכת, masechet,
there was a whole story about him and about how he was
causing anguish to תלמידי חכמים talmidei chachamim and whatever.
He came and he passed by them. Okay, so אמר ליה חד
לחבריה, amar leh chad le'chavrei, one said to the other, נקום מקמיה
דבר אוריין הוא, nekum mikamei de'bar oryan hu, let's stand up, this
guy's a he knows a lot of תורה. Torah. אמר להו לא
ומקמי פלגא נקום? Amar lehu lo umikmi palga nekum?
We should stand up for... Somebody that's divisive? He's the one that
if you again remember from the beginning of the מסכת, Masechet, he
caused מר עוקבא Mar Ukva a lot of pain and eventually he
was taken in chains and so on. So אדהכי אתא, Adehachi ata,
so while they were debating whether or not to stand up for
him, he came over to them. אזל לגבייהו Azal legabeihu and he
said to them: שלמא לכו מלכי, Shlama lechu malchi, שלמא לכו מלכי.
Shlama lechu malchi.
So presumably this story is here because we were talking about being
כפילת שלום, Kefilat shalom, and that's exactly what he was doing. He
was in שלום עליכם shalom aleichem, kings, שלום עליכם shalom aleichem, kings,
he was talking to them in this honored way and calling them
kings and expressing his enthusiasm for seeing them. אמרו ליה, Amru lei,
they said to him: מנא לך דרבנן איקרו מלכי? Mena lach de-rabbanan
ikru malchi? Where did you hear this idea that sages are called
kings? That that's a proper way to refer to us? אמר להו,
Amar lehu, דכתיב, De-chtiv, בי מלכים ימלוכו, Bi melachim yimlochu, the פסוק
pasuk in משלי Mishlei where תורה Torah is speaking says: Through me
kings have their reign. אמרו ליה, Amru lei, so therefore the people
through תורה Torah makes somebody into a king. אמרו ליה, Amru lei,
they said to him: ומנא לך דכפלינן שלמא למלכי? U-mena lach de-kafliinan
shlama le-malchi? And where do you know that when you encounter somebody
who's a king or somebody who's seen of as a king, you
say שלום עליכם Shalom aleichem שלום עליכם, Shalom aleichem you do it
twice? אמר להו, Amar lehu, דאמר רב יהודה אמר רב, De-amar Rav
Yehuda amar Rav, מניין שכופלין שלום למלך? Minayin she-koflin shalom le-melech?
Because I have a tradition from רב יהודה אמר רב, Rav Yehuda
amar Rav, how do you where do you know you double the
שלום, shalom, peace when you welcome a king? שנאמר, She-ne'emar, the פסוק
pasuk says: ורוח לבשה את עמשי ראש השלישים. Ve-ruach lavsha et Amashai
rosh ha-shlishim.
Spirit took over עמשי, Amashai, the head of the troops, and of
course it's the end of the פסוק pasuk that's significant. It's quoted
here on the side: לך דויד ועמך בן ישי שלום שלום לך.
Lecha David ve-imecha ben Yishai shalom shalom lecha. Peace, peace to you
דוד. David.
So it's a פסוק, pasuk, but I also have it as a
rabbinic tradition. This guy really seems like he wasn't one of the
social class of the rabbis, but he knew his stuff. That's what
they said: בר אוריין. Bar oryan. אמרו ליה, Amru lei, לטעום מר
מידי. Litim mar midi.
So they said: Oh, well let's talk. You're nice, clearly you know
תורה. Torah. Would you like to have a snack? Would you like
to eat some of our food? אמר להו, Amar lehu, he said
to them: הכי אמר רב יהודה אמר רב, Hachi amar Rav Yehuda
amar Rav, אסור לאדם שיטעום כלום עד שיתן מאכל לבהמתו. Asur le-adam
she-yitim klum ad she-yiten ma'achal le-vehemto. So apparently he knew the traditions
of רב יהודה אמר רב. Rav Yehuda amar Rav. No,
I have to go, I have to go feed my animals, and
it's אסור asur to eat anything before you feed your animals. שנאמר,
She-ne'emar, ונתתי עשב בשדך לבהמתך. Ve-natati esev be-sadecha le-vehemtecha.
First it says: I will give the grass to your animals. ואחר
כך ואכלת ושבעת. Ve-achar kach ve-achalta ve-savata. And then: Eat and be
sated. So fascinating way to end this whole tractate here. Here he
was, not only we learned earlier that he caused problems to this
מר עוקבא, Mar Ukva, here not only was he a בר תורה,
Bar Torah, but he was deeply respectful to the rabbis and he
had this whole morality about giving your בהמה behema first, giving your
animal first.
He seemed like a perfect person who's not of the rabbinic class,
but of somebody who
really respects and has the proper behavior towards the rabbis. So I
wonder if that's a little bit of getting at this whole
דרכי שלום. Darchei Shalom. The whole idea of דרכי שלום, Darchei Shalom,
there's an element of that about like reciprocity. It's not just
about to the
non-Jews: Well, we don't want them to be mean to us. There's
an actual value of acting in ways that encourage positive interactions and
encourage
interactions and a type of a peaceful society in which people are
respected and act in respectful and considerate ways to one another. That
could be seen as the larger point of דרכי שלום. Darchei Shalom.
What type of society do we want to construct and we want
to live in? So here we were talking about negotiating an עם
הארץ Am Haaretz and a חבר Chaver and so on. Here was
somebody that was perceived of as negative, and they were questioning whether
to approach him in a way of דרכי שלום, Darchei Shalom, and
he actually approached them in a way of דרכי שלום. Darchei Shalom.
So I think that that's probably, I don't know if that's intended
or not, but that's an interesting comment on the whole sort of
discussions of דרכי שלום Darchei Shalom that were part of this פרק.
perek. Okay, we now turn the page and we begin the sixth
פרק. perek. It's called האומר Ha-omer or sometimes it's called התקבל, Ha-titkabel,
which is the second word in it, more distinctive than האומר. Ha-omer.
Okay, and let's take a look at this. We get finally are
back to normal גיטין Gittin discussions.
האומר התקבל זה גט לאשתי. Ha-omer hitkabel zeh get le-ishti. Somebody says
to a שליח, shaliach, receive this גט get for my wife. או
הולך גט זה לאשתי, O holech get zeh le-ishti, or deliver this
גט get to my wife. אם רוצה לחזור יחזור. Im rotze lachazor
yachazor. He can change his mind any up to the minute it
gets delivered. Because even though he said: Receive this for my wife,
the wife did not appoint this person as her שליח, shaliach, as
her agent. So, and this is something that is to her detriment,
to be divorced it's assumed to be to her detriment. We had
this whole משנה mishnah way at the beginning if you remember. Anyway,
this is assumed to be to her detriment. So therefore, this guy
can be a representative of the husband to give the גט, get,
but the גט get is not final until the woman receives it.
So since he said receive, we're going to re-interpret receive, he can't
receive it for her, but we're going to interpret receive as deliver
it and have her receive it. But in either way though, she's
not yet divorced and therefore he can reverse it. himself until it
gets delivered.
האשה שאמרה התקבל לי גיטי. Ha-isha she-amrah hitkabel li giti. Now if
the woman appoints a שליח shaliach and says go to my husband
and he's ready to give me a גט get and receive my
גט get for me, then אם רצה לחזור לא יחזור. im ratza
lachazor lo yachzor. After the husband gives this שליח shaliach a גט,
get, the wife's שליח, shaliach, then it's final. He cannot retract it.
ולפיכך אם אמר לו הבעל, U'l'fichach im amar lo haba'al, therefore if
this שליח shaliach of the woman comes to the husband and the
husband changes it around a little bit, there's a way in which
the husband can still can still have an a window to change
his mind. Okay, he just don't give it to the שליח shaliach
as the agent of the woman, and change the parameters. And here's
how he's going to change the parameters. If he says אי אפשי
שתקבל לה, Ee efshi shetikabel lah, I don't want you to receive
this גט get on her behalf, אלא הולך ותן לה, ela holech
v'ten lah, here, I'm not giving it to you as her שליח,
shaliach, as her agent. I am not prepared that my giving it
to you represents my giving of it to her. What I am
prepared to do is to make you my agent to deliver it
to her. In that case, then he the agent, then he becomes
a double agent, ha-ha, then he becomes the agent of the שליח
shaliach of the husband, and then the husband can divorce the wife
up until he can change his mind up until the point it
gets delivered. אם רצה לחזור יחזור, Im ratza lachazor yachzor, if he
wants to retract he can retract. רבן שמעון בן גמליאל אומר אף
האומרת טול לי גיטי אם רצה לחזור לא יחזור. Rabban Shimon ben
Gamliel omer af ha-omeret tol li giti im ratza lachazor lo yachzor.
So Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel says even if the wife says to
the שליח shaliach rather than receive my גט get for me, if
she says I pick it up for me, take it for me,
so that is a good making him a good
שליח לקבלה, shaliach l'kabbalah, שליח shaliach to receive the גט, get, and
the husband cannot retract. Okay, clear, presumably the חכמים chachamim might disagree.
Maybe pick it up for me is not is not what the
wife is empowered to do. The wife's role is to receive it,
not to take it. So, but he says, no, we interpret it
to mean receive. All right, so let's take a look now at
the גמרא. Gemara. אמר ליה רב אחא בריה דרב אויא לרב אשי,
Amar lei Rav Acha brei de-Rav Avya le-Rav Ashi, so Rav Acha
brei de-Rav Avya said to Rav Ashi, טעמא דלא שויתיה איהי שליח
לקבלה. ta'ama d'lo shavitia ihi shaliach l'kabbalah. The reason in the beginning
of the משנה, Mishnah, right, we understand, right, that that that he
can retract is because this person has not been made a שליח
shaliach for the wife. Okay, meaning and to some degree what תוספות
Tosafot says is the point of the גמרא Gemara is because when
he says receive this גט get for my wife,
you know, that if he were a if the person were a
שליח, shaliach, obviously it would be final. So the משנה Mishnah is
teaching the case that he said receive this גט get for my
wife, like it's almost like crazy, of course he can't do that,
he's not a שליח, shaliach, right? Why does the משנה Mishnah even
have to teach you that that doesn't work? Obviously he can't give
it to the שליח shaliach for it to work right now. But
to teach you that we're talking about a case where the wife
did not make this person a שליח. shaliach. Okay, so that's that's
what he's saying. It's the משנה Mishnah is teaching you that these
cases of receive this גט get for my wife or take this
גט get to my wife don't work because this person has not
been made a שליח shaliach to receive the גט. get. Okay, הא
שויתיה איהי שליח לקבלה, Ha shavitia ihi shaliach l'kabbalah, had the wife
made him a שליח shaliach to receive the גט, get, רצה לחזור
לא יחזור, ratza lachazor lo yachzor, right,
he could not retract. And that's certainly true by the first case
when he says receive this for my wife, if the wife had
made this person a שליח shaliach for קבלה, kabbalah, of course that
would be final. But what he that's not a חידוש. chiddush. The
חידוש chiddush is the second case of הולך ותן לה, holech v'ten
lah, take this גט get to my wife. What happens if the
wife says to the שליח, shaliach, be my שליח shaliach to receive
it, and when the שליח shaliach goes to the husband, the husband
doesn't say receive it for her, he says the second case in
the משנה, Mishnah, take this to her. Do we understand that when
he says take this, but he's speaking to a שליח לקבלה, shaliach
l'kabbalah, is that mean take this and on her behalf and be
divorced? Or no, take this, convey this to her, which is more
what הולך holech means, convey this to her, and I'm not buying
into you being a שליח לקבלה, shaliach l'kabbalah, you are going to
be a שליח הולכה. shaliach holacha. So that is the question. So
he says, I'm going to infer from the משנה, Mishnah, since the
first case works when he's a שליח לקבלה shaliach l'kabbalah and the
husband can't retract, the same would be true about the second case.
Okay,
so the גמרא Gemara says, אי שויא שליח לקבלה רצה לחזור לא
יחזור. ee shavya shaliach l'kabbalah ratza lachazor lo yachzor. שמע מינה, Shema
mina, so we can see from this הולך כזכי דמי, holech k'zachi
dami, that when you say הולך, holech, take this, it's like you
said take this and take possession of it on behalf of this
person. Okay, so and that if you might remember way back at
the beginning of the מסכת masechet was a whole discussion when somebody
says that to somebody, take this for my slave, does a slave
automatically become free? Is הולך holech like זכי? zachi? So here there's
a הולך holech and that was the person that wasn't even made
a שליח shaliach to receive it. Here you have somebody made a
שליח shaliach to receive it, does הולך holech override that and turn
them into a שליח shaliach of to deliver it or does it
make it like, "Here, take this on her behalf"? And the גמרא
Gemara is saying that since the first case would work if he
and it would be an effective גט get if he was a
שליח לקבלה, shaliach le-kabala, the same would be true about the second
case, and this shows you that הולך holech is like זכי. zachi.
So, שמע מינה הולך כזכי דמי. sh'ma mina holech kezchi dami. So
the גמרא Gemara says לא, lo, so רב אשי Rav Ashi said
back, "I don't buy that inference. לא אמינא לך הולך לאו כזכי
דמי. lo amina lach holech lav kezchi dami. If you said הולך,
holech, it would not work. Okay, ויתקבל גט לאשתו איצטריכא ליה." ve-itkabel
get le-ishto itztaricha leh. So then why presumably teach the case of
התקבל, itkabel, receive? Presumably that's only put there to teach us that
it would be different if the person was a שליח shaliach for
קבלה. kabala. But you who's saying that it wouldn't be different in
the second case if he was a שליח לקבלה, shaliach le-kabala, what
is the חידוש chidush of the first case of התקבל? itkabel? דסלקא
דעתך אמינא, de-salka daitecha amina, I might have thought הואיל ובעל לאו
בר שויי שליח לקבלה הוא, ho-ilu ba'al lav bar shavei shaliach le-kabala
hu,
so since the husband cannot make this guy a שליח shaliach for
קבלה, kabala, אף על גב דמטא גיטא לידה af al gav de-mata
gita le-yadah לא להוי גיטא, lo lehvei gita,
even when she gets the גט get it wouldn't work, קמשמע לן
דהתקבל והולך קאמר, kamashma lan de-itkabel ve-holech kama,
"Receive it and bring it to her," is what he is saying.
Okay, so what does that mean? It means that the first case
of התקבל גט זה לאשתי itkabel get zeh le-ishti is seen as
unnecessary. It's seen as extra and trying to teach you something. Okay,
because obviously it doesn't work when you say to somebody who's not
a שליח shaliach for קבלה, kabala, "Take this גט get from my
wife,"
and be she should be divorced right now. Obviously she won't be
divorced right now. So the first approach said it's coming to teach
you that the whole both cases of the משנה Mishnah would be
different if she made a שליח shaliach for קבלה, kabala, and that
teaches you that הולך holech is כזכי. kezchi. That if she made
a שליח לקבלה, shaliach le-kabala, even if he said הולך, holech, it
would be immediately effective. The response back is, no, that's not what
the case of התקבל itkabel is coming to teach. התקבל itkabel was
coming to teach you the case itself, it is a חידוש. chidush.
Because if he says, "Receive this גט get for my wife," then
maybe even if it's delivered to the wife it doesn't work because
he never made this person a שליח shaliach to deliver it. He
just made this person said, "I want you to receive it for
her." So it really is a חידוש. chidush. The חידוש chidush isn't
that it doesn't work now. Of course it doesn't work now, he's
not a שליח לקבלה. shaliach le-kabala. The חידוש chidush is it does
work when he delivers it and even though he said, "Receive it,"
it means, "Make this גט get work for my wife, deliver it
and have her receive it." Okay, so now what we are saying
is that the first case of the משנה, Mishnah, receive it, it
doesn't work immediately because he's not a שליח לקבלה, shaliach le-kabala, but
it will work if it's delivered because receive it means make her
receive it, deliver it. The second case where he says, "Deliver it,"
obviously it won't work until it gets delivered. And the question that
we have is when the wife says to a שליח, shaliach, "Be
my שליח לקבלה," shaliach le-kabala, if the husband says, "Receive it," that's
your standard case, that works. But what if in that case he
says, "Bring it to my wife"? Does that change him into a
שליח shaliach for הולכה? holacha? Or does that "Bring, take it to
my wife," mean like take it for my wife and make it
immediately effective? And that's the question whether הולך holech is כזכי. kezchi.
You might be thinking that the next case in the משנה Mishnah
of אי אפשי, i efshi, "I don't want it this way, do
it this way," is relevant, which it is, what the גמרא Gemara
will look at when we continue this tomorrow.